"Can a Plant-Based Diet Reverse Type 2 Diabetes?"
Diabetes is a leading
cause of death worldwide
with an estimated
1.5 million deaths each year
directly attributable
to diabetes,
primarily type 2 diabetes.
And the disease is a major cause
of other health complications;
kidney failure, heart attacks,
strokes,
and lower limb amputations.
Along with those conditions
goes rising healthcare costs.
For example,
in the United States,
diabetes makes the list for
the top five medical conditions
accounting for a third
of all medical expenditures.
And spending more than doubled
over 20 years.
Diabetes is the only disease
for which cost per person
has increased significantly
for these top five
medical conditions,
coming in close
to $3,400 per person.
The majority of those costs
come from prescription medications.
And, while diabetes medications
can be a very important tool
for controlling
blood glucose levels,
what if there were another way?
Could a plant-based diet
be the solution,
not only to diabetes prevention
but to type 2 diabetes treatment?
And not just any treatment,
but actually with the goal
of diabetes remission.
The American College
of Lifestyle Medicine
convened a group of experts including
representatives from major groups
like the American
College of Cardiology,
the American Heart Association,
the Academy
of Nutrition and Dietetics,
the list goes on,
who reviewed the available
evidence on dietary interventions
for type 2 diabetes
treatment for remission,
and reached agreement
on three key issues.
First, type 2 diabetes remission
should be defined as having HbA1c,
a marker of blood
glucose control,
below 6.5 percent for
at least three months
with no surgery, devices,
or active drug therapy
being used to
lower blood sugars.
Second, diet, as a primary
intervention for type 2 diabetes
can achieve remission in many adults
and is related to the intensity
of the intervention.
And, finally, the big one,
diet as a primary intervention
is the most effective
in achieving remission
when emphasizing whole,
plant-based foods,
with minimal consumption
of animal products.
Why is this so profound?
In addition to experts from all
these different groups agreeing,
nutrition therapy
is not usually discussed
in the context of remission,
but rather as an add-on
to go with whatever drugs are
prescribed for blood sugar control,
or as a way to help delay
or prevent complications.
In this consensus statement,
remission was endorsed
as the clinical goal
for type 2 diabetes,
and it is most
optimally attained
using a whole-food,
plant-based diet
that emphasizes
unrefined plant foods
and eliminates
or minimizes animal foods
and refined foods,
and, of course,
includes moderate exercise
that we all should be
getting on a regular basis.
Oh, and critically,
the intervention meant to
help with type 2 diabetes
shouldn't cause adverse
health effects itself,
such as very low-carb
ketogenic diets,
which might appear to help
with blood glucose control,
but in fact produce negative
cardiometabolic side effects.
Here's what can happen after
treatment with a high-fiber,
low-fat, plant-predominant diet.
The authors wanted to show
the feasibility
of medication reduction
and type 2 diabetes remission
using a lifestyle-based
intervention
without drastically
cutting calories.
Patients with diabetes
were referred to a wellness clinic
and received information on
adopting a plant-predominant diet
along with addressing
other major risk factors.
Importantly, these patients
didn't self-select
into a specific lifestyle
medicine treatment program.
They were simply presented
with lifestyle prescriptions
as part of their routine
medical care.
What a wild idea!
Here's a visual
of the plant-predominant diet
they were encouraged to follow—
about 95 percent plants
with a lot of veggies, beans,
whole grains, fruits, and seeds.
The researchers took
a closer look at those patients
who had adopted the recommended
plant-centric diet
and successfully decreased
their blood sugar
to non-diabetic ranges.
How many people
experienced remission?
More than a third of them
and almost half with HbA1c
levels below 6.5 percent
were able to discontinue
all medications—
they just hadn't yet reached
the three consecutive months
of testing required
to get the label
for "official remission."
A lifestyle-based intervention,
primarily focused on education
about the benefits
of a plant-predominant diet
for diabetes treatment
and remission,
resulted in decreased
blood glucose markers
to levels achieving
both reduction of medications
and remission
of type 2 diabetes,
highlighting the promising potential
for a plant-predominant diet
to confer immediate
and long-term benefit
including reducing complications
of type 2 diabetes.